JACOB COLVIN

Platform, Site Reliability, and Software Engineer

Cincinnati, Ohio

@ me@jacobcolvin.com

jacobcolvin.com

in colvinjm

MacroPower

ABOUT

My expertise lies in **Site Reliability Engineering**, enriched by a deep focus in **Software** and **Platform Engineering**. My passion lies in building robust **developer platforms**, crafting maintainable **infrastructure as code**, and architecting systems in a way that is simple and straightforward. My experience as a developer, with a focus on **Go** and **Python**, enables my ability to create platforms that are not only reliable and maintainable, but also enjoyable to use.

EXPERIENCE

84.51° / The Kroger Company

■ Hybrid / Cincinnati, Ohio

May 2016 - Current

Senior Site Reliability Engineer

- April 2021 Current
- Successfully transitioned our **Kubernetes (AKS)** platform from being a set of internal-only clusters, to a production-grade platform hosting multiple critical applications that were collectively responsible for driving over \$100MM operating profit; participated in an **on-call rotation** to ensure compliance with SLAs.
- Designed a fully **GitOps** workflow for Kubernetes cluster management, using **FluxCD**, **Terraform**, and **Renovate**, which reduced manual cluster administration work by over 1,000 hours per year.
- Rolled out **Datadog** as a unified observability platform for both **Azure** and on-premises systems, leveraging **Vector**, **Fluentd**, and **OTEL Collectors** for assorted telemetry pipelines; this enabled the deprecation of multiple disparate observability solutions and saved over \$500k annually.
- Maintained multiple on-premise Cloud Foundry / Tanzu Application Service instances; supported cloud migration efforts which
 moved applications from Cloud Foundry to Kubernetes.
- Developed **Python** application for scaffolding template repositories, as well as centralized **Helm charts** and related **GitHub Actions**, which collectively saved developers more than 3,000 hours during the first year in production.
- Empowered developers to efficiently and independently troubleshoot their applications by acting as lead subject-matter expert for observability platforms; headed support and maintenance of all observability tooling, including **Datadog**, **Grafana**, **Prometheus**, **Thanos**, **Jaeger**, **Dynatrace**, **Fluentd**, **OpenTelemetry Collectors**, and **Vector**.
- Developed **Python** library to centralize instrumentation for **Prometheus** metrics, **OpenTelemetry** tracing, structured logging, and **pprof** profiling, with support for **FastAPI**, **gRPC**, **Databricks** notebooks, and more, which both delivered a positive and consistent experience with our observability platforms, and saved developers over 1,000 hours.
- Led development of multiple **Prometheus exporters** using **Go**, utilizing **Redis** for caching, distributed workers with pub/sub and leader election, **CEL** for custom rule evaluation, **Cue** and custom tooling for validation, and Go text templating.
- Created multiple Jsonnet libraries for Prometheus and Alertmanager configuration, saving over 100 hours per year.
- Contributed fixes to Grafana, Thanos, Jaeger, and other upstream Git repositories.

Versatilist Engineer

☐ January 2020 - March 2021

- Created and administered multiple Azure environments using Terraform in Azure DevOps; said environments frequently included
 resources such as Databricks workspaces, Datafactory instances, Key Vaults, Storage Accounts, and Postgres databases.
- Enhanced our **Prometheus** ecosystem by adding high-availability and long-term storage via **Thanos**, thus allowing consumers of Prometheus to track SLOs and KPIs over years instead of days.
- Assisted a mix of seven development and data science teams with **Azure** migration, **Terraform**, **Grafana** dashboards, **Prometheus** alerts, **GitHub Actions**, and **Azure DevOps** pipelines; acted as technical liaison to increase speed and accessibility of support.

ICT Co-op

May 2016 - December 2019

- Designed a **C#** API layer over several legacy systems, and a SPA using **TypeScript** with **React**, to both assist with support, and improve velocity towards deprecation of legacy systems.
- Created a **Prometheus exporter** for **SonarQube** data, along with corresponding dashboards, rules and alerts, to allow security team to gather relevant KPIs.
- Automated Red Hat Linux VM deployment through ServiceNow, via interactions with Satellite, vCenter, SolarWinds and Ansible.
- Designed a custom web framework using **PowerShell** and **Bootstrap** for executing administrative tasks and aggregating events and metrics from many distinct products.
- Automated many miscellaneous tasks using PowerShell, VBA, Bash and PL/SQL in Bash; created and documented Automic
 workflows with Bash and SAS ODS.
- Interfaced with BOSH and Hadoop to design custom Pivotal Cloud Foundry monitoring solution.

EDUCATION

B.S. Information Technology, University of Cincinnati	📋 Aug 2015 – April 2020
Summa Cum Laude, CeDiD: 20H0-3K9Z-JEND KEY PROJECTS	
• An open-source project that seeks to completely automate vincluding Telegraf, Prometheus, and Grafana.	Center monitoring, by orchestrating a small ecosystem of containers
• Paper: https://scholar.uc.edu/concern/student_works/jw82	7c971
• Technologies: Docker, C# / .NET Core, TypeScript, React	
Homelab	MacroPower/homelab
Infrastructure-as-code for my homelab / personal cloud. De bare metal (Talos) and multiple Hetzner cloud environments	efines multiple interconnected Kubernetes clusters, spanning across (k3s-on-MicroOS).
Technologies: Talos, Cilium, ArgoCD, Helm, Jsonnet, Terrafor	m
Prometheus Video Renderer	• MacroPower/prometheus_video_renderer
• Just for fun, completely impractical tool that allows you to e	ncode audio and video as Prometheus metrics.
 Featured on the Grafana blog: https://grafana.com/blog/2021/07/30/how-to-use-grafana 	-and-prometheus-to-rickroll-your-friends-or-enemies
Technologies: Go, Jsonnet	
Analytics Panel Plugin	• MacroPower/macropower-analytics-panel
• Grafana panel plugin that injects JavaScript into dashboards, in turn exports Prometheus metrics for display in (you guess	which reports user session information to a backend Go server, which ed it) Grafana.
Over 1MM downloads, featured by Giant Swarm: https://www.giantswarm.io/blog/grafana-ception-or-how-v	ve-do-grafana-analytics-giant-swarm
Technologies: TypeScript, React, Go	
Wakatime Exporter	• MacroPower/wakatime_exporter

- Prometheus exporter and Grafana dashboards for Wakatime coding statistics.
 Over 100k downloads
- Technologies: Go